today's video i want to show you how we
can run python in our browser using pi
script we all know that javascript is
the king of the web this is not because
developers chose to make it king of the
web is because there was no other choice
the programming language that browsers
have always understood is javascript
javascript and javascript only until now
python is another programming language
that has a beautiful beautiful syntax a
huge developer community that is using
python for building back-ends ui
applications ai data science among many
other things now imagine how cool would
it be if we could use python in the
browser instead of javascript how cool
would it be if we could bring all this
developer community all this ecosystem
all these amazing packages to the
browser that would be amazing that would
be awesome that is exactly what pi
script was created for pi script is a
framework that allows developers to
build dynamic applications using only
html and python it was created by
anaconda which they are already a big
player in the python space and the way
it works is pretty cool but that comes
later first i want to show you the code
and give you a tiny tour of what you can
do with typescript by building a tiny
application that i like to call the
python casino but first as always let's
start with a hello world to start using
pi script all we have to do first is
create an html document and on the head
we're going to load pi script by
importing a javascript file i am also
going to add pico css to make our page
look pretty and that's it that's how
easy it is to get started with pi script
to use it now all we have to do is open
a tag called pi dash script and inside
of this tag we can write python code
like for example print hello world now
using the live server extension of
visual studio code i am going to run a
server and we will see how the print
statement shows up on the screen and
that's it that is hello world we just
run python in our browser as you can see
it's pretty cool already but this is not
the best inside of the pi script tags we
can also import modules from the python
standard library like for example the
datetime module and we can use it just
like we would do it on a normal python
file but that is not all with another
tag called pi m we are able to import
python files and even other packages to
our application for this we put the pi m
tag in the head and we write down the
packages or files that we want to use
here for example we could import numpy
or matplotlib if we wanted to do some
data visualization if i create a python
file and write a tiny function inside of
it i can later add the file to the pi
end and i can later use the function in
my html also if you don't really like
writing python code inside of the html
because it looks ugly and doesn't look
good you can just import your python
files using the src attribute of the pi
script tag but again that is not all so
we have seen how we can run python code
in the browser which is already super
super cool but it still is not the best
the best in my opinion is the fact that
if we want to we are able to communicate
with the html on the page from our
python code to see this let's build our
python casino for this we are going to
create an input and a button the input
will be a number input where the user
will guess a number between 1 and 50. we
will give ids to the input and the
button and we will add a special
attribute to the button element the
attribute is called pi's on click which
allows me to tell pyscript to execute a
python function when the button is
clicked the function we want to run when
the user clicks the button is called
play game but we haven't created that
function yet so let's do so but remember
if you want to learn to code for free
with me and you want to learn things
like python or javascript or react or
react native or redox or graphql or go
or type it among many other things for
free and with subtitles in google then
please click the link below and i will
see you there
on the python side i want to first get
the value of the input that i created on
my html for this i will use element
which allows me to get an element by the
id now that we have the input element i
can access its value and put it on a
variable after that we will get a random
number between 1 and 50 using the random
module from the python standard library
if the number the user chose and the
number the machine picked are the same
that means the user won else the user
lost but we have to communicate this
outcome to the user for this we're going
to create an h1 tag in our html and
we're going to give it an id
back in the python file using element
again we're going to grab that h1 tag
using a very similar api to javascript
we will access the inner text of the h1
and we will tell the user if they won or
lost and at the end we're going to clear
the input so the user can play again and
we are done as you can see the user can
now write things on the input they can
click on the button and they will see a
result we are manipulating the html from
our python code now please in the
comments let me know how cool do you
think this is i think this is amazing
it's so freaking cool on the pi script
github repository you can find many
examples of what is possible with
pyscript for example this code that
shows you how easy it is to make and
show a python plot on the web importing
numpy and matplotliff before we finish
let's look at the black magic being used
to make pi script work as we saw at the
start if we want to use pi script we
have to import a javascript file in our
html does this mean that pi script is
running on javascript
not really pi script works thanks to
something called pilodite and web
assembly piotide is a port of c python
which is an interpreter of python but
compiled to web assembly webassembly
isn't a programming language it is more
of a compilation target just like when
you for example finish writing a c
program and you decide to compile it to
windows or linux or macbook intel or
macbook m1 the same way you can build
something in c like c python is and
compile that to web assembly now
webassembly is a binary code format that
browsers understand as well so basically
pi script is using webassembly to embed
a c python interpreter in our browser
and because of the magic of webassembly
we are also able to talk to the html
even though what we've seen today is
pretty cool pi script is still very very
young now it completely exploded on
github it already has more than 10 000
stars but it's very better and it's very
unstable so we're going to maybe have to
wait for a long time for the
documentation to grow more for the
software to be more stable and for
things to work well for now we can just
try to hack and build experimental stuff
with pi script and see if we find any
bugs if we find any problems we can
report them and help in the github
repository to make this beautiful crazy
and awesome idea guru
now i am curious about what you think
let me know in the comments what is your
opinion about pi script are you excited
are you afraid are you going to use it
do you want to learn pi script should i
make a longer video on pi script making
something more complex please let me
know i am so curious about what the
developer community thinks thank you so
much for watching as well with and don't
forget if you want them to code for free
with me and with subtitles in hangul
please click the link below and also if
you like this content and you would like
to support the channel please leave a
like and subscribe it's free for you
it's just two clicks but it helped me a
lot thank you for watching as always
stay happy stay free eat kimchi come
hang me down saturn hey yo see you in
the next one bye